Roberto Bigazzi

Ph.D in Computer Vision and Deep Learning

Modena, Italia

□+39 334 8756245 | ➡roberto.bigazzi.1995@gmail.com | 🏕 robertobigazzi.it | 🛅 roberto-bigazzi | 📂 R. Bigazzi

Summary_

I'm a Post-Doc Researcher at the University of Modena and Reggio Emilia, in the AlmageLab research laboratory supervised by Professor Rita Cucchiara. The main topics of my research are Computer Vision and Deep Learning, particularly on Embodied AI tasks and challenges. I pursued my Ph.D. at AlmageLab research laboratory after completing my Master's Degree in Computer Science and Engineering at the Polytechnic University of Milan, with Professor Marco Gribaudo. During my Ph.D. program, I spent a period as a visiting student researcher at Stanford University in the Autonomous Systems Lab (ASL) directed by Professor Marco Pavone.

Knowledge and Technical Skills _____

Domains Visual Navigation, Multimodal Learning, Natural Language Processing, Reinforcement Learning, Deep Learning

Programming Python, Java, Javascript, C++, C#, C, MATLAB, SQL, Microcontroller Programming (Arduino)

Frameworks and Other PyTorch, OpenCV, Numpy, Pandas, ŁTEX, Scikit-learn, Tensorflow, Keras, ROS, Git, Android Programming, MySQL

Languages Italian (Mothertongue), English (Proficient TOEIC (C1), FCE (B2))

Education

University of Modena and Reggio Emilia

Modena, Italy

Post-Doc Researcher: Computer Vision and Deep Learning

Mar. 2023 - present

Research on Visual Navigation and Multimodal Learning

University of Modena and Reggio Emilia

Modena, Italy

Doctor of Philosophy in Information and Communication Technologies: Computer Vision and Deep Learning

Nov. 2019 - Mar. 2023

• Multimedia Data Learning at Almagelab under the supervision of Prof. Rita Cucchiara

Stanford University Stanford, California, United States

Visiting Student Researcher May 2022 - Aug. 2022

Research on Visual Navigation at Autonomous Systems Lab (ASL) under the supervision of Prof. Marco Pavone

Polytechnic University of Milan

Milan, Italy

Master of Science in Computer Science and Engineering

Sep. 2017 - Oct. 2019

• Thesis with Prof. Marco Gribaudo: "Enhancing Spatial Navigation in Robot-Assisted Surgery: a case study"

Technische Universität Wien

Vienna, Austria

Erasmus+ Exchange Semester

Oct. 2018 - Feb. 2019

Polytechnic University of Milan

Milan, Italy

Bachelor of Science in Software Engineering

Sep. 2014 - Sep. 2017

Istituto Istruzione Superiore Roncalli

Poggibonsi (SI), Italy

Liceo Scientifico Tecnologico

Sep. 2009 - Jul. 2014

Experience _____

AlmageLab - University of Modena and Reggio Emilia

Modena, Ital

Research Fellow

Nov. 2019 - present

Research during the Doctorate at AlmageLab covering these topics in Computer Vision: Deep Learning, Reinforcement Learning, Visual Navigation, Robotics, Machine Learning, Domain Adaptation.

Prometeia Bologna, Italy

Lecturer
Python and Machine Learning course for Banco BPM

Nov. 2021

IFOA BolognaBologna, ItalyLecturerMar. 2021 - Apr. 2021

Data Analysis and Data Visualization course

IFOA Modena Modena, Italy

Lecturer Jan. 2021 - Feb. 2021

Deep Learning, Artificial Intelligence e Neurolinguistic Processing (IBM, SAS) course

Polytechnic University of Milan

Milan, Italy

Master Thesis Mar. 2019 - Sep. 2019

Master Thesis with the title "Enhancing Spatial Navigation in Robot-Assisted Surgery: a case study" supervised by Professor Marco Gribaudo. Abstract: Use of augmented reality in order to assist surgeons during surgery for prostatectomies, trying to solve the problem of identifying unambiguous landmarks from the video recorded by the camera of the "da Vinci Surgical System" and speeding up the steps needed to apply the 3D model superimposed to the prostate.

Cyber-Physical Systems Group - Technische Universität Wien

Vienna, Austria

Project Developer Oct. 2018 - Jan. 2019

Project performed on the creation of a vertical farming system during the course of Internet of Things of the Professor Ezio Bartocci at TU Wien. Main topics of the project: BLE Communication, Microcontroller Programming, Cloud Computing, Arrowhead Framework.

Pubblications

2023 International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA)

Embodied Agents for Efficient Exploration and Smart Scene Description

Roberto Bigazzi, Silvia Cascianelli, Lorenzo Baraldi, Marcella Cornia, Rita Cucchiara

The development of embodied agents that can communicate with humans in natural language has gained increasing interest over the last years, as it facilitates the diffusion of robotic platforms in human-populated environments. As a step towards this objective, in this work, we tackle a setting for visual navigation in which an autonomous agent needs to explore and map an unseen indoor environment while portraying interesting scenes with natural language descriptions. To this end, we propose and evaluate an approach that combines recent advances in visual robotic exploration and image captioning on images generated through agent-environment interaction. Our approach can generate smart scene descriptions that maximize semantic knowledge of the environment and avoid repetitions. Further, such descriptions offer user-understandable insights into the robot's representation of the environment by highlighting the prominent objects and the correlation between them as encountered during the exploration. To quantitatively assess the performance of the proposed approach, we also devise a specific score that takes into account both exploration and description skills. The experiments carried out on both photorealistic simulated environments and real-world ones demonstrate that our approach can effectively describe the robot's point of view during exploration, improving the human-friendly interpretability of its observations.

2022 Robotics and Automation Letters (RA-L) + International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA)

Focus on Impact: Indoor Exploration with Intrinsic Motivation

Roberto Bigazzi, Federico Landi, Silvia Cascianelli, Lorenzo Baraldi, Marcella Cornia, Rita Cucchiara

Exploration of indoor environments has recently experienced a significant interest, also thanks to the introduction of deep neural agents built in a hierarchical fashion and trained with Deep Reinforcement Learning (DRL) on simulated environments. Current state-of-the-art methods employ a dense extrinsic reward that requires the complete a priori knowledge of the layout of the training environment to learn an effective exploration policy. However, such information is expensive to gather in terms of time and resources. In this work, we propose to train the model with a purely intrinsic reward signal to guide exploration, which is based on the impact of the robot's actions on the environment. So far, impact-based rewards have been employed for simple tasks and in procedurally generated synthetic environments with countable states. Since the number of states observable by the agent in realistic indoor environments is non-countable, we include a neural-based density model and replace the traditional count-based regularization with an estimated pseudo-count of previously visited states. The proposed exploration approach outperforms DRL-based competitors relying on intrinsic rewards and surpasses the agents trained with a dense extrinsic reward computed with the environment layouts. We also show that a robot equipped with the proposed approach seamlessly adapts to point-goal navigation and real-world deployment.

Spot the Difference: A Novel Task for Embodied Agents in Changing Environments

Federico Landi, Roberto Bigazzi, Marcella Cornia, Silvia Cascianelli, Lorenzo Baraldi, Rita Cucchiara

Embodied AI is a recent research area that aims at creating intelligent agents that can move and operate inside an environment. Existing approaches in this field demand the agents to act in completely new and unexplored scenes. However, this setting is far from realistic use cases that instead require executing multiple tasks in the same environment. Even if the environment changes over time, the agent could still count on its global knowledge about the scene while trying to adapt its internal representation to the current state of the environment. To make a step towards this setting, we propose Spot the Difference: a novel task for Embodied AI where the agent has access to an outdated map of the environment and needs to recover the correct layout in a fixed time budget. To this end, we collect a new dataset of occupancy maps starting from existing datasets of 3D spaces and generating a number of possible layouts for a single environment. This dataset can be employed in the popular Habitat simulator and is fully compliant with existing methods that employ reconstructed occupancy maps during navigation. Furthermore, we propose an exploration policy that can take advantage of previous knowledge of the environment and identify changes in the scene faster and more effectively than existing agents. Experimental results show that the proposed architecture outperforms existing state-of-the-art models for exploration on this new setting.

2020 25th International Conference on Pattern Recognition (ICPR) (Oral Presentation)

Explore and Explain: Self-supervised Navigation and Recounting

Roberto Bigazzi, Federico Landi, Marcella Cornia, Silvia Cascianelli, Lorenzo Baraldi, Rita Cucchiara

Embodied AI has been recently gaining attention as it aims to foster the development of autonomous and intelligent agents. In this paper, we devise a novel embodied setting in which an agent needs to explore a previously unknown environment while recounting what it sees during the path. In this context, the agent needs to navigate the environment driven by an exploration goal, select proper moments for description, and output natural language descriptions of relevant objects and scenes. Our model integrates a novel self-supervised exploration module with penalty, and a fully-attentive captioning model for explanation. Also, we investigate different policies for selecting proper moments for explanation, driven by information coming from both the environment and the navigation. Experiments are conducted on photorealistic environments from the Matterport3D dataset and investigate the navigation and explanation capabilities of the agent as well as the role of their interactions.

OTHER RESEARCH WORK

2023 22st International Conference on Image Analysis and Processing (ICIAP) (Honorable Mention for ICIAP Best Paper Award)

Towards Explainable Embodied Navigation and Recounting

Samuele Poppi, Roberto Bigazzi, Niyati Rawal, Marcella Cornia, Silvia Cascianelli, Lorenzo Baraldi, Rita Cucchiara

2021 19th International Conference on Computer Analysis of Images and Patterns (CAIP)

Out of the Box: Embodied Navigation in the Real World

Roberto Bigazzi, Federico Landi, Marcella Cornia, Silvia Cascianelli, Lorenzo Baraldi, Rita Cucchiara

2021 21st International Conference on Image Analysis and Processing (ICIAP)

Embodied Navigation at the Art Gallery

Roberto Bigazzi, Federico Landi, Silvia Cascianelli, Marcella Cornia, Lorenzo Baraldi, Rita Cucchiara

Under Review

Indoor Semantic Region Mapping: Language-grounded Visual Recognition for Embodied Navigation

Roberto Bigazzi, Shreyas Kousik, Lorenzo Baraldi, Rita Cucchiara, Marco Pavone

Under Review

AIGeN: An Adversarial Approach for Instruction Generation in Vision-and-Language Navigation

Niyati Rawal, Roberto Bigazzi, Lorenzo Baraldi, Rita Cucchiara

Under Review

UNMuTe: Unifying Navigation and Multimodal Dialogue-like Text Generation

Niyati Rawal, Roberto Bigazzi, Lorenzo Baraldi, Rita Cucchiara

Program Committees

2023	Evaluator, ELLIS Ph.D. Program	
2021-now	Peer Reviewer, IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters (RA-L)	
2022-now	Peer Reviewer, IEEE Geoscience and Remote Sensing Letters (GRSL)	
2022-now	Peer Reviewer, IEEE Pattern Recognition Letters (PRL)	
2020	Peer Reviewer, Transactions on Multimedia Computing Communications and Applications (TOMM)	
2024	Peer Reviewer, IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA)	Yokohama, Japan
2024	Peer Reviewer, IEEE/CVF Winter Conference on Applications of Computer Vision (WACV)	Waikoloa, USA
2023	Peer Reviewer, ACM International Conference on Multimedia	Ottawa, Canada
2023	Peer Reviewer, 22nd International Conference on Image Analysis and Processing (ICIAP)	Udine, Italy
2023	Peer Reviewer, IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS)	Detroit, USA
2023	Peer Reviewer, IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA)	London, UK
2022	Peer Reviewer, IAPR International Conference on Pattern Recognition (ICPR)	Montreal, Canada
2022	Peer Reviewer, 21nd International Conference on Image Analysis and Processing (ICIAP)	Lecce, Italy
2021	Peer Reviewer, ACM International Conference on Multimedia	Chengdu, China
2020	Peer Reviewer, ACM International Conference on Multimedia	Seattle, US (virtual)

Teaching Activities

- 2020-23 **Teaching Assistant,** Computer Architectures
- 2021-22 **Project Tutor,** Al for Automotive
- 2021-22 **Lecturer,** Al for Automotive: SLAM Lessons
- 2020-21 **Project Tutor,** Neural Network Computing, Al and Machine Learning for Automotive
- 2019-20 **Project Tutor,** Computer Vision and Cognitive Systems

Presentations

- 2019-23 **Presenter,** "Into The Future" University Orientation Program
- 2022 **Presenter,** "Humanities & Intelligence" Laboratory
- 2021 **Presenter,** "In the mind of robots, how Al teaches robots to navigate" Laboratory

Languages_

Italian

Mother tongue

English

Writing: Fluent, Reading: Fluent, Listening: Fluent

- TOEIC (C1): Grade 960/990
- FCE (B2): Grade C

Certificates ____

SCHOOLS AND WORKSHOPS

2021	4th Advanced Course on Data Science and Machine Learning, ACDL	Siena, Italy
2017	Interactive Internet of Things e Smart Object Design Course, Polytechnic University of Milan	Milan. Italy

2013 European Computer Driving Licence Certificate, ECDL

Interests_

Professional Computer Vision, Artificial Intelligence, Robotics, Internet of Things, UI Design

Personal Technology, Gaming, Sport, Cinema

According to law 679/2016 of the Regulation of the European Parliament of 27th April 2016, I hereby express my consent to process and use my data provided in this document and application for recruiting purposes.